Guide to the Enoch Hodson Papers 1881-1893
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Enoch Hodson Papers
1881-1893
Montana State University Library, Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 461, MtBC, us
Hodson, Enoch, 1842-1892
.6 linear feet
The Enoch Hodson Papers consist primarily of daybooks and ledgers for the operations of Hodson's Mill and general store. Also included is a time book for payment of his employees from June of 1887 to March 1890. Also included are miscellaneous business papers includes a receipt for membership in the knights of Pythias, a liquor sales ad, a doorplate from William and Hoyt, and bills to some customers.
Biographical Note
Enoch Hodson was born in Marion County, Indiana April 8, 1842. He was one of the early pioneers of Montana. He moved to Bannack in what was then the Idaho Territory, in 1863. He took an active part in the vigilante movement before moving to Gallatin County in the early 1870s. In 1880 he ran for sheriff of Gallatin County on the Republican ticket but lost the election to Charles P. Blakeley. A well respected member of the community, Hodson ran a sawmill and a general store in the Bozeman area. He married a Miss Thompson of Jefferson County some time before he settled in Gallatin County. The two of them had 8 sons that all lived to maturity. Enoch Hodson died November 22, 1892 in Helena, Montana at the age of 60. He suffered a severe injury to one of his eyes and he died during the operation to repair it at the hospital in Helena.
The Hodson papers consist primarily of daybooks and ledgers for the operations of Hodson's Mill and general store. Also included is a time book for payment of his employees from June of 1887 to March 1890. One folder of miscellaneous business papers includes a receipt for membership in the knights of Pythias, a liquor sales ad, a doorplate from William and Hoyt, and bills to some customers. The ledgers include several important clients such as Lester S. Wilson, the Chisolm Brothers, Rocky Fork and Cooke Railroad Company, Valley Ranch, and several other important people and businesses in the Gallatin Valley.
This collection is open for research.
Financial ledgers and a few personal effects were donated to Montana State University by Merrill G. Burlingame of Bozeman, Montana in 1966.
Gallatin River Valley (Wyo. and Mont.)-Commerce
General stores-Montana-Gallatin County; Sawmills-Montana-Gallatin County
Business records-Montana-Gallatin County
Businessmen-Montana-Gallatin County
Forestry and Forestry Products; Retail Trade; Montana
- Day Book, Enoch Hodson, September 1881-November 1883 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Day Book, Enoch Hodson, March 1884-March 1886 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Day Book, Hodson's Mill, 1887 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Day Book and ledger, Hodson's Mill, 1882-1884 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Ledger, Hodson's Mill, 1882-1883 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Day Book, Enoch Hodson, July 1887-April 1889 (Box-folder 2/1)
- Employee time book, June 1887-March 1890 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Pocket Day Book, Hodson's general store, December 1887
  - Pocket Day Book, Hodson's general store, January 1888
  - Pocket Day Book, Hodson's Mill, November 1887-December 1887
- Receipt for Knights of Pythias membership, December 1893 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Bill to Mary King for Labor and Merchandise, February 20, 1887 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Liquor distributor ad from W. L. Perkins and Company (Box-folder 2/3)
- Door Plate from William and Hoyt (Box-folder 2/3)
- Bill to M. P. Coal Company, August 1, 1885 (Box-folder 2/3)